[Music]
foreign
country by country cancer rates have
shown up to what 70-fold variation in
the incidence of prostate cancer
worldwide with low rates in parts of
Asia and Africa and high rates in North
America Australia New Zealand and
Northern Europe and here's the map of
prostate cancer mortality could Dairy
consumption have something to do with it
given Northern Europeans Americans
Australians drink a lot of milk whereas
most non-caucasians in the world are
lactose intolerant but just because a
country drinks a lot of milk and has a
lot of cancer doesn't mean the
individuals within that country that are
drinking the milk are getting the cancer
that's why we need cohort studies where
you find out how much milk people drink
and follow those individuals over time
and see if those who drink more milk get
more cancer
there have been dozens of such studies
done uh put them all together and
intakes of total dairy products
including low fat milk were indeed
associated with increased prostate
cancer risk the question is why maybe
it's just all the calcium they found
that the more calcium people consume the
higher their risk of prostate cancer
yeah but most people get their calcium
from dairy so how do we know this isn't
just a dairy effect before we start
worrying about kale and other non-dairy
sources of calcium it'd be nice to see
Dairy calcium teased out from non-dairy
calcium intakes and that's exactly what
they did yes the more calcium from dairy
sources the higher the risk of cancer
but non-dairy sources of calcium were
found to be protective
so it wasn't a calcium effect it was a
dairy effect this suggests that other
components of dairy may be to blame
they suggest it's the animal protein
boosting the levels of a
cancer-promoting growth hormone called
igf-1 insulin like growth factor one if
you look at 28 studies involving nearly
28 000 people this is what's called an
albatross plot and he studied to the
right of this line shows the link
between igf-1 levels and dairy product
milk specifically or dairy protein
consumption and any study hitting this
line or over shows a significant
association with higher igf-1 levels
this could also explain why plant-based
diets can be so protective put watch and
weight cancer patients on a whole food
plant-based diet for a year and no chemo
no radiation Lifestyle Changes only and
get a significant reduction in PSA
levels indicative of tumor shrinkage
their bloodstream becoming nearly eight
times better at suppressing the growth
of cancer cells do biopsies and you can
show changes in gene expression a down
regulation of critical cancer genes
effectively switching off cancer growth
genes at a genetic level whereas if you
instead eat lots of dairy after prostate
cancer diagnosis you may suffer a 76
percent higher risk of death overall and
a 141 percent increased risk of dying
specifically from your cancer
without igf-1 the milk protein casing
appears to be a cancer cell
proliferation promoting Factor
increasing the growth of prostate cancer
cells at least in a Petri dish and the
same thing with whey the other major
animal protein in Dairy see nearly 100
percent of advanced prostate cancers
Thrive by up-regulating a growth enzyme
called Tor and dairy protein boosts
torsingling even higher which only makes
sense right calves have to grow like 40
times faster than human babies and so
cow's milk has to be packed with growth
promoters not to mention the hormones in
milk especially from cows who are
already pregnant again
this commercialized milk production by
pregnant cows releases uncontrolled
amounts of bovine steroid hormones into
the human food chain and so the
combination May well explain the
observed association between High Dairy
consumption and increased risk of
prostate cancer
from an evolutionary perspective the
persistent abuse of the growth promoting
signaling system of bovine milk by
humans over their entire lifespan not
just drinking milk during infancy
maintains the most important Hallmark of
cancer biology this sustained
proliferative signaling to grow grow
grow and so there's this interest in
trying to define the safe upper limits
of long-term milk and dairy intake for
the prevention of the most common Dairy
promoted cancer in men but if you look
at diet and cancer guideline
recommendations yeah milk may increase
risk of prostate cancer however no
recommendation was provided for cutting
down on Dairy because the evidence for
prostate cancer conflicted with
decreased risk of colorectal cancer High
Dairy intake is associated with
increased prostate cancer risk but
decreased colon cancer risk so it's like
you know alcohol maybe an in toxic
hating carcinogen but policymakers
hesitate to introduce you know effective
alcohol policies or even to support the
addition of cancer warning labels for
fear they might undermine any possible
health benefits of alcohol use now I've
talked about how the purported benefits
of alcohol appear to be evaporating is
dairy really protective against colon
cancer
if you put all the cohort studies
together where they measure Dairy
consumption then follow people for years
to see who got cancer milk and total
Dairy consumption was indeed associated
with a reduction in colorectal cancer
risk one of our deadliest cancers now
people who drink more milk just happen
to tend to exercise more smoke less
drink less eat less meat which could
explain some of the association however
many of the studies adjusted for these
kinds of confounding factors more likely
it was the protective effects of the
calcium which may bind up
pro-inflammatory bile acids in the gut
though high fat dairy products like
cheese may actually increase bile acids
explaining why the cheese appeared to
cancel out the calcium benefit
so might we be able to get the Best of
Both Worlds by consuming non-dairy
calcium sources
if you randomize people to calcium
supplements you can get a significant
reduction in recurring colon polyps
which can otherwise turn into cancer
though calcium pills have been
associated with adverse cardiovascular
effects and so the best of all worlds if
you want to take a precautionary
approach in terms of nutrition in cancer
is to obtain calcium through low oxalate
dark green leafy vegetables beans split
peas chickpeas and lentils or if
necessary calcium fortified foods such
as soy Ramen milk
[Music]
thank you